<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Developer and Self Hoster Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Developer and Self Hoster Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 23:15:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.octopusx.de/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Enter the Fediverse</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/enter_the_fediverse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 23:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/enter_the_fediverse/</guid>
      <description>Being ancient, as one finds themselves at one point in live, I still remember the times before Facebook. I got into it briefly in my late teens but then dropped it like a stone once I realised that I was spending way too much time doom scrolling&amp;hellip; And that was in the 00&amp;rsquo;s, I find it hard to imagine getting into it now and I am feeling am grateful that having the entire &amp;ldquo;facebook&amp;rdquo; domain blocked on my pihole really is not a problem for anyone in my home.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bluewind - let&#39;s make a smart bluetooth fan smart again!</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/bluewind/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 23:39:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/bluewind/</guid>
      <description>In a recent surprising turn of events, I got to connect with some listeners of Jupiter Broadcasting shows, one of which happens to be involved in organizing the Berlin Hack and Tell meetup, which is a cool monthly event where people do short demos of cool projects they had hacked together. After some chatting with this funky group of tech enthusiasts, I was encouraged to present some of my project that seem to be a perfect fit for Berlin Hack and Tell, so ahead of submitting my lightning talk, I wanted to make a blog post here first to put down in words how this project came to be and what it actually is, in case anyone fancies finding out more about it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refact Helm Chart</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/refact_chart/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 20:19:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/refact_chart/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s get charting! I honestly wasn&amp;rsquo;t expecting to be writing this post quite so soon, but it turns out that the library chart we adapted from the k8s-at-home is extremely versatile and that their old github actions translate very well to my new Teapot instance. So, let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at what it takes to create an application chart and publish it with our awesome new setup.
Starting point The starting point is our hand-written set of kubernetes templates that we wrapped into a helm chart to deploy in our kubes and gpus tutorial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teapot - host your own helm chart registry</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/teapot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:24:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/teapot/</guid>
      <description>For a while I wanted to host my own helm chart registry and automate my chart build, release and deployment processes. As a homelaber, a one man band, the more things happen on their own without my manual involvement the better. Self hosting to me also means self reliance and local storage for most things needed in order to build and run my services, and getting my own registry is getting one step closer to that goal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kubes and GPUs</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/kubes_and_gpus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 13:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/kubes_and_gpus/</guid>
      <description>Graphics cards are once again available. The AI hype is on for sure, but it&amp;rsquo;s not as much of a craze as the the mining fad of yesteryear. Finally, graphics-based compute is semi-affordable again, especially if you look to the second hand market. Having dabbed my toes in the world of self hosting large language models I have come to realize that hosting those on CPUs only is not going to give me a good insight into what this tech is capable of.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reasonably Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/reasonably_large_language_models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 20:20:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/reasonably_large_language_models/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s no such thing as free lunch right? I think that openAI are learning this hard way as they are burning all kinds of cash and are no longer providing me with free tokens to use. I must say, I quite liked using CodeGPT in VSCode. Thankfully we have had a bunch of developments lately in the realm of self hosted local AI initiatives, following Facebook&amp;rsquo;s Llama2 release. At the same time more and more applications have plugins that lets them interact with openAI API compatible local LLMs, including VSCode!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nextcloud Conference 2023</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/nc_conf_2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 09:23:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/nc_conf_2023/</guid>
      <description>Although I do a lot of semi-public speaking in a professional capacity, I have recently given my first talk at a conference for fun! I use nextcloud as the backbone of my open source, privacy focused self hosting infastructure, the WebDav/CalDav integrations really enable my family to largly de-google their smarphone experience. Happy to give something back to a project I sincerely respect. This short lightning talk was based on my previous blog post about how I designed my backup and restore procedures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Encrypted Volumes</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/encrypted_volumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 23:38:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/encrypted_volumes/</guid>
      <description>When I started self hosting services I was afraid of storing my non-sensitive data encrypted. As I played with different kinds of hardware setups, hypervisors and hosting strategies I have made a decision to not encrypt the volumes attatched to my docker containers. This was so that when I inevitably break stuff, I can easily still access everything and move it to a new home where it can be used again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Backup and Restore</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/backup_restore/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 21:47:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/backup_restore/</guid>
      <description>So, you have a backup. Wait, two backups? And a third one off site too?? But&amp;hellip; You have tested the restore procedure, right? No!? Damn son, what do you need a backup for if you don&amp;rsquo;t even know if you can restore it???
If you can&amp;rsquo;t restore it, you don&amp;rsquo;t really have a backup&amp;hellip; Protecting your data doesn&amp;rsquo;t end at having a 3-2-1 backup. Whether you are self hosting services or handle company data in the cloud it pays to have a practiced plan for bringing your services and data back to life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HA in the homelab</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/homelab_ha_edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 14:46:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/homelab_ha_edition/</guid>
      <description>In general I like things simple. I need technology to work for me and provide value without having to dedicate extraordinary amount of time to it. When it comes to running a homelab this is especially true, since I am likely spending my own free time setting things up and maintaining my infrastrcuture. At a certain point in the life of my homelab however I found myself hosting services for my wife, family and some friends.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wireguard &#43; Linode &#43; Unraid = Profit</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/wireguard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 15:24:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/posts/wireguard/</guid>
      <description>I have been using Unraid as a platform to manage my storage at home as well as hosting a few basic services for me and my family for a good few years now. Despite having a fairly fast internet connection I was not able to expose those services to the internet however as my home router does not support dynamic DNS. As an alternative I knew that I could get a small VM with a public IP address which could host a VPN endpoint for me to build a permanent tunnel to my Unraid box.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mastodon Feed</title>
      <link>https://blog.octopusx.de/feed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.octopusx.de/feed/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
